<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An easy method to know the causes and signs of the humour most ruleth in the body and to avoid thereby things hurtful: as also to enable men to give better account of the state of their bodies, when they are diseased to the physitian, and not hazard the lives of themselves and their freinds by only urging him to prophesy (and that often falsily) the disease by onely the inspection of vrine.</title>
            <title>Scholae medicae. English</title>
            <author>La Framboisière, Nicolas Abraham de, b. 16th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04984</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121086</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856275</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856275</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21804</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04984)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21804)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 841:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An easy method to know the causes and signs of the humour most ruleth in the body and to avoid thereby things hurtful: as also to enable men to give better account of the state of their bodies, when they are diseased to the physitian, and not hazard the lives of themselves and their freinds by only urging him to prophesy (and that often falsily) the disease by onely the inspection of vrine.</title>
                  <title>Scholae medicae. English</title>
                  <author>La Framboisière, Nicolas Abraham de, b. 16th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title, A1r.</note>
                  <note>A translation of "De causis morbificis", from "Scholae medicae".</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hygiene --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21804:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <head>An eaſy Method to know the Cauſes and Signs of the Humour moſt ruleth in the Body, and to avoid thereby things hurtful: as alſo to enable men to give better account of the ſtate of their Bodies, when they are diſeaſed to the Phyſitian, and not hazard the Lives of themſelves and their Freinds by only urging him to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy (and that often falſely) the Diſeaſe by onely the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection of Vrine.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He antecedent or foregoing ſignes of fulneſſe are ſuch cauſes as breed plenty of blood,
<note place="margin">Antecedent ſignes of ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</note> ſuch as are,</p>
            <p>The good temper of the whole Body, but chiefly of the Liver and Heart, with a moderately hot and moiſt temper.</p>
            <p>The Age increaſing, for Children and ſuch as are conſtituted betwixt them both, have much blood, becauſe they are not farr diſtant from the principles of Nature.</p>
            <p>Spring ſeaſon, Becauſe in the Spring the blood is moſt plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, for the cold then remitts, and moiſture puts forth it ſelf.</p>
            <p>A Region temperate, but chiefly.</p>
            <p>A more liberall diet of meates of good juice, and well tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as too much plenty and affluency of the beſt meat and wine, a life void of cares, full of rejoycing, with moderate and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable exerciſe, and ſleeping mean.</p>
            <p>Suppreſſing of cuſtomary vacuation of blood of its own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, or medicinal a long time intermitted, ſuggeſts mattter to fulneſſe.</p>
            <p>The conſequent or following ſignes of fulneſſe of blood,
<note place="margin">Conſequent ſignes of ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> are incidents which demonſtrate plenty of blood to be contained and reign in the body: ſuch as are</p>
            <p>The colour of the face and body ruddy beyond cuſtome, or mingled with red and white.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21804:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
An equall ſwelling of all the veins,</p>
            <p>The exte<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the filled veſſels and ſtretcht with fulneſſe of blood ma<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the view.</p>
            <p>An exten<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> weariſomneſſe coming of it ſelf, wherein the body and all the joynts through wearineſſe are hardly moved, and the hand is hardly contracted into the fiſt: For a diſtend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weariſomneſſe comes, when as the greater veins ſwelling with plenty, empty themſelves into the leſſer, whence it happens that the muſcles are filled and diſtended.</p>
            <p>An overfull maſſe of body, of abundance of fleſh ſprings from plenty of blood.</p>
            <p>The habit of the body meanly fleſhly, bedewed with a milde, gentle, and breathing heat: becauſe a habite mouerately fleſhy, betokens a temperate nature which is full of blood.</p>
            <p>The manners of mind pleaſant and ſweet, calm and gentle: For a temperate and mild diſpoſition of mind, is a mark of a temperate habit of body.</p>
            <p>Simpleneſſe and ſtupidity of mind for ſimplicity and ſtupid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mind proceeds from blood; heavineſſe of the head, by reaſon of plenty of vapours aſcending to the brain.</p>
            <p>Deep and for the moſt part pleaſing ſleep, in the which things are repreſented by dreams full of joyfulneſſe and pleaſantneſſe, ſhining like light, or adorned with flowers.</p>
            <p>The pulſe great, ſtrong and full. For the veines being full the conjunction of their mouthes with the Arteries, doe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe ſome of their plenty into them: but the Arteries being full, do yeeld ſuch a pulſe, not onely in the wriſt, but in the temples alſo, the fingers, and the extremity of each part, conſpicuous by a trouble ſome beating.</p>
            <p>The breathing is more difficult and thicker then of cuſtome, chiefly after exerciſe, becauſe the muſcles of the breaſt through plenty of blood, are more ſlow in their motion, whence the breathing is more frequent in reſpect of its uſe, but leſſer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the inward capacity of the breaſt is ſtreightened.</p>
            <p>Speedy caſting forth of blood by ſtoole, the haemorrhoides, monthly evacuations, urine, ſpittle or noſe.</p>
            <p>A facility in bearing of much bleeding.</p>
            <p>Much ſweat continually flowing through the whole courſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21804:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->of a diſeaſe, doth deelare the preſence of fulneſſe.</p>
            <p>Moreover, if the party diſeaſed hath been accuſtomed to be vexed frequently with diſeaſes coming of fulneſſe, as a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent fever, inflammation: for all inflammation cometh by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flux of blood.</p>
            <p>Cacochimy or ill juice is three fold, Cholerick,
<note place="margin">Antecede<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſignes of ch<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler.</note> Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and Flegmatick. Ill juice proceeding of Choler, ariſeth from ſuch antecedent cauſes as heap up plenty of choler. Such are</p>
            <p>A temper hot and dry, for in men of hot and dry tempers, much Choler is ingendred, becauſe the cholerick humor is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to their complexion.</p>
            <p>The age conſtant and flouriſhing, ſuch as endures from the 25 yeare to the thirtieth, for yellow choler exceeds in the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting age, becauſe the natural heat is much more dry and intenſe, then it was before, a great part of the firſt inbred humor, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it was overwhelmed as it were, being conſumed.</p>
            <p>The ſummer ſeaſon, for in ſummer Choler is moſt abounding, becauſe bloud by the incompaſſing ayre is rendred more hot and dry.</p>
            <p>The dry conſtitution of the time; for drineſſe effects a bili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous quality in the humors.</p>
            <p>A region hot and dry, but chiefly a diet foregoing hot and dry.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, exerciſes, labour, anger, cares, watching, abſtinences and wants, heap up much Choler: as alſo, voluntary evacuation of choler ſuppreſſed, or ſuch as was accuſtomed to be avoided by art intermitted, by vomit, the belly, Urine, or ſweats.</p>
            <p>The conſequent ſignes of choler,
<note place="margin">The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſignes of choler.</note> immoderately exceeding in the body are;</p>
            <p>The colour of the face, eyes, and whole body pale, yellow or citrin colour, approaching to that of the yellow Jaundice. Or,</p>
            <p>Black, for if the temperament do much exceed in heat, the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour appears black.</p>
            <p>The habit of body dry, lean, and ſlender, for ſlender or ſpare men for the moſt part are cholerick. Alſo haiery bodies, for the temper hot and dry is very hairy.</p>
            <p>The hair yellow, for yellow hair is the dreggy excrement of yellow Choler.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21804:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
Much more alſo the haire that is black, for the haire becomes black when the vapour being burnt by the force of heat, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crement is changed into an exact ſmuttineſs. But yellow when as it is leſſe burnt.</p>
            <p>The largeneſs of the veins being diſtended by the force of heat; for they who have large veins are of a hotter nature, but contrarily they are colder whoſe veins are ſmaller, and ſtricter. For it is the work of heat to dilate, and as it were puffe them up.</p>
            <p>A heat to the touch, ſmart and biting.</p>
            <p>Swiftneſs to anger, ptopenſion to wrath and revenge, prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mind, and cheerfulneſs.</p>
            <p>The ſenſes are quick, ſharp, and nimble, the wit ſharp and induſtrious. For ſharpneſs of wit, and induſtry proceed from the billious humor.</p>
            <p>Sleep little and light, and with much toſſings and tumblings unquiet.</p>
            <p>Watchings almoſt continuall: for immoderate watchings proceed either from the diſtemper of the braine alone, or from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of Cholerick humour.</p>
            <p>Dreams full of Warr, fury and fire.</p>
            <p>The pulſes vehement, ſwift, frequent and hard.</p>
            <p>Bitterneſs of taſte, inappetency, vehement and unſatiable thirſt, gnawings in the mouth of the ſtomach, and from thence falling ſickneſs, Convulſions, faintings through paine of the mouth of the ſtomach.</p>
            <p>Vomiting and dejection by ſtoole cholerick.</p>
            <p>The belly daily bound.</p>
            <p>The Urine yellow, fiery, ſharp, and with ſmall Cholerick di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes frequent. As the diſeaſe called <hi>Cholera,</hi> the Feaver <hi>terti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and burning, creeping ſores and fretting, cholerick puſhes breaking forth over the whole body.</p>
            <p>The purging of Choler profitable, and eaſie of bearing, and the uſe of coole things gratefull and delightfull, becauſe they bridle the fierceneſs of Choler, as hot things exaſperate it: Whence a cholerick diſeaſe, by adminiſtring hot things, is made more fiery,<note place="margin">Antecedent ſignes of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy.</note> as on the other part, by cool things it is remitted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cacochymy,</hi> melancholick is known firſt by the Cauſes which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21804:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->congeſt a larger portion of melancholly and black choler in the body; of which ſort are.</p>
            <p>A naturall temper cold and dry, with the weakneſſe of the ſpleen, or a hot temper indeed at the firſt, but by change turned into cold. For if any which before was hot and dry, by aduſtion hath generated much black choler, he verily is beſides that he is dry, and cold, forthwith alſo melancholike.</p>
            <p>The age inclining, which is extended from the Thirtieth year of age to the Fourty nineth; for Choler aduſt aboundeth in the declining age, becauſe ſucceeding to youth, of all the ages the moſt Cholerick, receives unto it Choler aduſt.</p>
            <p>The Autumnall Seaſon, forasmuch as Choler aduſt is plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the fall of the leafe, becauſe this ſucceeding the Summer of all the parts of the year, the hotteſt and dryeſt entertaines from it burnt Choler.</p>
            <p>The manner of life, and frequent uſe of groſſe and earthly nouriſhment, ſueh as are courſe brown bread, Beefe, Hare, Goats fleſh, Veniſon, but moſt of all meates over-falted, groſſe Wines, dark, colour red, ill brewed Beere, or not well defaecated, old Cheeſe.</p>
            <p>A ſad condition of life, enfolded in many cares, buſineſſes, contemplations and ſtudy of Letters, no refreſhing or rejoycing the minde being interpoſed, or bodily exerciſe; For under this the natutall heat languiſheth, and the whole parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy wax groſſe, being lull'd aſleep by ſluggiſhueſſe.</p>
            <p>The cuſtomary vacuation of melancholly ſuppreſt, whether it was voluntary, as by the haemorrhoides, the Termes, by the Belly, or by the <hi>Varices</hi> or ſcab, or by Medicaments accuſtomed.</p>
            <p>The colour of the face and the whole body, dark, brown, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and ſwartiſh; ſometimes it is Univerſall and equall in the whole body, ſometimes mured with certain ſpots.</p>
            <p>Hardneſſe of the Spleen; Swelling, a weighty paine.</p>
            <p>The habit of the body dry and leane.</p>
            <p>The Aſpect ſixed, horrid and mournfull.</p>
            <p>Fear and ſadneſſe, ſilence, ſolitarineſſe, a vaine forging of things that are not, conſtancy and ſtability of minde. Becauſe that which is conſtant and ſixed in the minde, proceeds of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21804:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
A mind ſlow indeed to wrath, but fierce, and hardly appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable.</p>
            <p>Sleep turbulent, floating and toſſed with horrid dreames, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of dark things, Devills, Torments, Death, dead Carcaſſes</p>
            <p>Graves, which things are full of terrour.</p>
            <p>The pulſe is little, ſlow, rare and hardiſh.</p>
            <p>The appetite is often corrupted, yet ſometimes the hunger is like doggs hunger, ſowre matter, lining and ſucking the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach.</p>
            <p>Melancholy voluntarily breaking forth through over-plenty, by vomit, ſtool, urine, ſweates, or the hard knote or ſwellings in the veines.</p>
            <p>The Urine if no melancholy iſſue with the urine, is thin and white, but if any of it flow forth with the urine groſſe and black.</p>
            <p>Melancholy diſeaſes frequent.</p>
            <p>Medicaments that draw melancholy are conducefull, and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the diſeaſed: alſo all diet that breeds good and thin juice, is helpfull, but the contrary is hurtfull.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Antecedent ſignes of Phlegme.</note>The knowledge of phlegmatick ill juice is taken firſt from the cauſes which make large proviſion of phlegme; ſuch as are.</p>
            <p>A temper cold and dry.</p>
            <p>Old Age, which is extended from the 49th yeare, to the lives end. For in old age there is congeſted much excrementitious phlegme, through the want of naturall heate.</p>
            <p>The winter ſeaſon: Becauſe the Winter fills the body with phlegme, by reaſon of multitude of raine.</p>
            <p>Conſtitution of the ſeaſon moiſt: for the moiſture of the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bient Aire heaps up phlegmatick ſuperfluities.</p>
            <p>The immoderate uſe of cold and moiſt nouriſhment, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlarge drinking wateriſh Liquors.</p>
            <p>A diet overfull, unſeaſonably taken in, the former not being digeſted, likewiſe all ſatiety and gluttony.</p>
            <p>A ſedentary life led in ſlothfull idleneſſe, ſpecially in places wateriſh and moiſt.</p>
            <p>Long ſleep, eſpecially after eating.</p>
            <p>The ſuppreſſion of phlegme wont to be voided either by mouth or belly, which was long accuſtomed either by it ſelfe or by Art.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21804:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
The conſeqnent diſcoverers of phlegme ruling in the body,
<note place="margin">Conſeqent ſignes of Phlegme.</note> are ſuch as are,</p>
            <p>The colour of face and body whitiſh, ſometimes of Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colour, or blewiſh, the face ſomewhat ſwoln, and the whole habit of the body vaſt and over-grown with fat, foraſmuch as groſe and fat folk are cold and phlegmatick; for fat is alwayes generated by the refrigeration of the habit.</p>
            <p>The veins and arteries ſmall and narrow paſſaged, becauſe they contain but little blood.</p>
            <p>The skin white, ſoft, and without haire; for the temper cold and moiſt is exceeding ſmooth.</p>
            <p>Hair white; for white hair comes of phlegme.</p>
            <p>The feminine Sex for women, are by nature colder then men.</p>
            <p>The manners and mind, and all the motions of the body ſlow with heavineſſe and ſloth, the ſenſes dull, the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blockiſh.</p>
            <p>Sleep is deep and heavy.</p>
            <p>Dreames filled with water, raine, ſnow and drowning.</p>
            <p>Heavineſs of the head.</p>
            <p>The pulſe ſmall, ſlow, rare, ſoft.</p>
            <p>Slow concoction, ſowre belſhings, loathing after eating.</p>
            <p>The Urine is white or pale, now thin, now thick, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with much ſetling.</p>
            <p>Phlegme voluntarily breaking forth by vomit or dejection, and a body overflowing with moiſture.</p>
            <p>White flux in Women.</p>
            <p>The cuſtome and frequency of phlegmatick diſeaſes, as ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings coming of phlegme, rheumes and the like.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever vacuation of phlegme, whether it ſhall fall to be by Art, or of it ſelf, is conducefull, meates, and hot drinkes, and all heating cauſes occurring are pleaſing and profitable.</p>
            <p>But ſalt phlegme, ſince it acquires unnatural heat either by mixture of choler, or putrefaction introduced: as it obtaineth the mixt cauſes of choler and phlegme, ſo after a manner it hath their mixt ſignes. For the moſt part it is knowne, by the taſte, itchings, and fowle ſcabs.
<note place="margin">Ancecedent ſignes of Winde.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Plenty of windes are raiſed in the body by a cold and moiſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21804:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->ſtomach, together with imbecillity of heate, whether it proc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed of ſimple diſtemper, or that it be contracted by the fault of the humors.</p>
            <p>The Spleen ſwelling, and obſtructed with melancholy, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the condoction of the ſtomach.</p>
            <p>Windy meates, and rawe fruits, as Cheſtnutts, beanes, Muſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rums.</p>
            <p>Immoderate drinking, and, and the overmuch floting of the ſtomach with liquid meates, as aiſo cramming and gluttony.</p>
            <p>Idleneſſe, much ſleep, the age, region and conſtitution of the ſeaſon cold.
<note place="margin">Conſequent ſignes.</note>
            </p>
            <p>When as by the former cauſes much wind is gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the ſtomach and gut Colon, chiefly on the left ſide, are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtended, and roare, as if they were toſſed with the windes: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſive paines coaſt about the whole body, wandring, as it were, too and fro.</p>
            <p>Frequent breakings forth of Winde are heard both by the mouth and belly, to which eaſe ſpeedily ſucceedeth: as alſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſingings, or ringings in the eares.</p>
            <p>Great proneſs to cholick paines, and other diſeaſes pſoceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Winde.</p>
            <p>Dreames of things ſwiftly running or flying, ſometimes alſo of thunder and tempeſts.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have by me a farre larger Tract on this ſubject, but this being more eaſy for common capacities, I thought fit to preſent it firſt <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> view; As this ſhall finde acceptance, and I encouragement, I ſhall ſend to light matters of greater moment than theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Farewell.</hi> That I may not ſeem to be a plagiary, the Author in <hi>Latine</hi> is <hi>Frambeſarius.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21804:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
